<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Akshat's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://olttwa.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://olttwa.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-18T04:31:38+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://olttwa.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Akshat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Humane and Effective Ways for Collecting Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://olttwa.com/blog/2017/03/17/humane-and-effective-ways-for-collecting-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-17T23:38:31+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://olttwa.com/blog/2017/03/17/humane-and-effective-ways-for-collecting-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blogpost will probably change your mind if:</p>

<ul>
<li>you think numbers matter while collecting feedback</li>
<li>providing feedback is mandatory for your users</li>
<li>feedback providers aren&rsquo;t incentivized in your system</li>
</ul>


<p>Disclaimer: This is oriented towards systems providing services
catered to a huge audience through various service providers. (e.g. GO-JEK,
Amazon, Uber, etc.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Feedback is information about how we are doing in our efforts to reach a
long-term goal. Keeping this in mind, I will explore what is wrong with
the current feedback system, how we can take better feedback and why we
should incentivize feedback givers.</p>

<p>Giving feedback shouldn&rsquo;t be mandatory. When a system sees more than a
million units of bookings per day, ratings in feedback too don&rsquo;t make
sense. At this rate, when we make giving feedback mandatory for the
user, ratings in feedback becomes bad data. There are 3 reasons for
that.</p>

<p>The first reason is a lower rating doesn&rsquo;t signify anything. For
example, when the result of my Mathematics examination came as 85 out of
100, this result doesn&rsquo;t point to the root cause of the problem. There
could be multiple reasons: I made a silly mistake; I understood
everything but the time provided wasn&rsquo;t sufficient; I hadn’t studied
some concepts; some questions were very difficult for my understanding
of the concept, etc.</p>

<p>The second reason is common knowledge that vendors are fired because of
lower ratings on their feedback. Many users I know give maximum
ratings on every feedback simply out of sympathy for the service
provider. A major cause for this sympathy is constant nagging of
service providers to give maximum rating on their feedback. We as
users understand that their very livelihood depends on our feedback
and end up providing false feedback.</p>

<p>The third reason is users do not revisit a platform immediately after
the booking ends. In case of a shoddy experience, users forget about it
by the next time feedback is asked of them, and involuntarily give the
maximum ratings as per their usual habit.</p>

<p>If we look at every user experience as the test of effectiveness in
reaching our goal, numbers in feedback end up creating unncecesary
stress amongst the entities under test; which in turn makes for a bad
experience for our end-user. I am saying that ratings as part of
feedback is bad data because it is skewed 85% in the favour of maximum
ratings. No real system can provide such flawless service in the long
run. Major flaws will remain hidden as they cannot be inferred from the
remaining 15% of the data.</p>

<p>I believe I have convinced you that numbers don&rsquo;t matter in case of
feedback. So the billion dollar question. How to take effective
feedback? To answer this question, we have to understand what value lies
in feedback. It has 2 values.</p>

<p>One value of feedback definitely is improvement of our service. In order
to ensure improvement, feedback should be direct. There should be no
positives or negatives, just plain feedback. Take tags for instance. We
can start with some tags like <em>All went well</em>, <em>Payment experience was
bad</em>, <em>Route taken was more time consuming</em>, <em>Other comments&hellip;</em> Turn
every unit of customer experience into a test. To take a thorough test,
our tags must be dynamic. We must improvise upon those tags. We should
turn feedbacks collected as <em>Other comments&hellip;</em> to tags based on their
frequency, and remove rarely used tags. Our tags must vary based on
location, service provider as well as user. If we add a new feature for
experimenting, we can add a tag for feedback of that feature as well.</p>

<p>Data validation becomes very easier in the long run if feedback is
direct. Some users' feedback will become more credible compared to
others. Incentivizing or punishing our service providers based on
specific improvements becomes a reality. We will have more confidence
approaching a service provider for improvement as we&rsquo;d have direct data
from our users.</p>

<p>Another value feedback provides is shaping the future of your business.
Feedback refers to the past, or at best, to the present. Wouldn&rsquo;t it be
awesome if sometimes users tell us what to do. There should be provision
to provide ideas everytime a user asks to give feedback. A text box
saying: <code>Is there any way we could have served you better?</code> on every
feedback screen will bring in ideas like these: <em>I prefer travelling in
a different vehicle</em>, <em>a refreshing drink would have been nice!</em> and so
on.</p>

<p>So to sum it up, we should not ask our users mandatorily for
feedback, expect them to give feedback when they feel there is room for
improvement or newer ideas pop into their heads. But why would any user
go to such great lengths to provide valuable input that drives our
business. The answer to every work well done is incentives. When we see
a user giving correct feedback more than 80% of the time (credibility of
the user is validated by feedback given by other users. Just think how
thrilled a user will be to know an idea he/she suggested has been
incorporated into the system.</p>

<p>After all, every system survives based solely on the loyalty of its
users. When the users believe they are part of the system, loyalty
grows. To gain loyalty, we must put the user in the driver&rsquo;s seat.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[o.l.t.t.w.a.]]></title>
    <link href="http://olttwa.com/blog/2017/03/17/o-dot-l-t-dot-t-w-dot-a/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-17T23:32:57+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://olttwa.com/blog/2017/03/17/o-dot-l-t-dot-t-w-dot-a</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I believe every decision we make in our lives, we make in order to have One
Less Thing To Worry About.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It is very simple. From the start, our parents educate us; try to
inculcate good values into us. The only goal they are trying to achieve
is that we&rsquo;ll have less things to worry about when we grow up. That is
how this philosophy seeps into our mind.</p>

<p>Ofcourse there is a trade-off between long-term and short-term goals.
When we keep persisting despite failures, it will be beneficial in the
long-term. When we decide to give up and give-in to distraction, it is
beneficial in the short-term. But the goal is simple - olttwa.</p>

<p>Many a times, we realize much later that our decisions have
given rise to hundred more things to worry about. For example,
fertilizers have caused imbalance in the biological ecosystem; automation has given rise to unemployment and
many more.</p>

<p>I am learning to design sustainable systems. Please comment here, reach out to me on
akshat.iitj@gmail.com, or twitter if you wish to discuss anything.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
